FX offers two products. The first one is a leverage product. It delivers leverage
on ETH and BTC without funding costs, without borrowing costs, users just pay a one-time
opening and closing fee. And that's it and in most cases they won't have to pay any fundings.
And the difference with regular CDP is that we abstract the looping so we give overexposure
to the collateral and we have this very innovative liquidation mechanism that prevents any hard
liquidation. FX protocol is an evolved CDP. Whenever people are longing the collateral,
it involves selling the stablecoin for more collateral. Different peg keeping mechanisms.
The first one is that stability tool. On FFX, the stability tool is a yeast strategy that takes
both FX USD and USDC as base assets. Each time FX USD is traded below one,
the USDC from the yeast strategy will buy FX USD in the market to put it closer to peg
and its change is traded above one, it's sold back for USDC and goes back to the stability tool.
Hey guys, I want to tell you about Gnosis, a collective of builders creating real tools
for real people on the open internet. Gnosis has been around since 2015. In fact,
it started as one of Ethereum's very first projects and today it's grown into a whole ecosystem
designed to make open finance actually work for everyday people. At the center of it all is Gnosis
Chain. It's a low-cost, highly decentralized layer one that's compatible with Ethereum and secured by
over 300,000 validators. So whether you're building a DAP, experimenting with DeFi,
or working on autonomous agents, Gnosis Chain gives you a solid, neutral foundation to build on.
But Gnosis is more than just infrastructure. It's also tools that people can actually use,
like circles for example, lets anyone issue their own digital currency through networks of trust,
not banks. And then there's Metri, it's their smart contract wallet that makes it easy to access
circles, manage group currencies, and even spend anywhere Visa has accepted thanks to their
integration with Gnosis Pay. All this is governed by Gnosis Dow, where anyone can propose, vote,
and help guide the network. And if you want to get involved, running a validator is super easy.
All you need is one GNO and some basic hardware. To learn more and start building on the open
internet, head to Gnosis.io. Gnosis, building the open internet, one block at a time.
Welcome to Epicenter. The show which talks about technologies, projects, and startups driving
decentralization and the global blockchain revolution. I'm Sebastian Guccio, and today I'm here with
Cyril, who is our core contributor at FX protocol. FX is a really interesting,
yield-bearing stablecoin that also utilizes a purpose market. There's an interesting stability
mechanism there that we'll get into. And also right now, I think it's probably one of the best
yielding stablecoins on the market, with their stability pool yielding somewhere around like 12,
13%. So that's really sort of compelling and interesting. And I wanted to talk to Cyril today
about FX and understand the core mechanism and also how they fit in the broader stablecoin landscape.
So nice to see you today. Thanks for joining. Hey, thanks Sebastian for having me. It's a
real pleasure to be here today. So you're actually based in France. I see you've got the Ethereum
France T-shirt. What's your background? How did you get interested in DeFi? Have you
worked at any of the big French protocols? I started DeFi because I got direct with the crypto
markets and I figured I wanted to make yields and that getting yield on stablecoins would be
somehow more predictable income than just betting on the market volatility. And I had a bit of
funds on my company, actually, and I went to the bank and I asked for yield opportunities to the
bank. And as a professional in France, they would offer me 0.15% APR with a six-month
lookup. And I figured it's 0.15% or 15%? No, no, 0.15, 0.15% with not 1%. Yeah, yeah.
So I figured it was a theft and I should find something else. And I heard about DeFi at that
point. And actually, I didn't hear about DeFi. I heard about Celsius. That was offering something
like 8% and next so as well. And I started putting euro there at that time. And I figured, okay,
how do these guys actually make yields? And this is how I heard about DeFi. And it was
right after the DeFi summer. And I bumped into a French community called DeFi France.
It sprinkles to maybe lobster dow, but for French people. And it's a group of DeFi passionate people
talking mostly about DeFi and with zero bullshit. It's mostly doing about building stuff. And there's
a lot of builders, actually, in the group. And I started by reading everything, every single message
in that group for months. And I learned a lot of stuff starting practicing DeFi as well and getting
involved into DeFi France by sharing what I learned from the community and organizing meetups
in Toulouse. And I've organized almost a meetup a month for the past three years. I just stopped
before this summer. And this is how I got to meet with people that came to the meetup to
talk about their projects and stuff like that. And how I got people to reach out to me to get my
opinion on different stuff. And regarding F of X, I did a meetup about F of X in September 23.
So right after the first iteration launch, I've been following Aladdin Dow, which is the
the Dow behind F of X and as well as concentrator and clever protocols. I've been following the
DAF since the beginning. And when I first read about F of X, I just loved the design. So I figured
I should make a meetup about it and share it on the community. And this is how I started to
contribute to the project. Cool. I think like doing meetups is such an underrated kind of low
lift thing that you can do early in your crypto journey. I organize a few meetups back in the day
Lil and the North of France. And like, yeah, I know, like, you know, Brian, my co-founder here at
epicenter, like also organize like quite a few minutes in Berlin. And it's such a great way,
like meet people who, you know, you don't necessarily see online, right? But like, they come out of
the woodwork for the meetups, right? And they built it's like great, great way to build connection.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah. One of this few cost systems left in which you can easily access to people that
make the ecosystem. And you can just give to the community and it will just bring so many
opportunities, you know, just by being genuinely sharing stuff, just meet people and it brings
opportunity. Yeah, I guess what I'm trying to say is like even, you know, even like 15 years
into crypto, there's still opportunity for people to like have to, like, encourage anybody to do
that. And like, what's the relationship? Like, well, what is Aladdin down in the relationship there?
And, you know, someone was already working on effects before you started contributing to it.
Yeah, it's a good question. Aladdin Dow is the Dow that builds F of X protocol. So it's the same
team, basically. And Aladdin started as an investment Dow, something like four years ago. And but it
quickly created its first protocol to just to get what was missing to them in the Defiled Enscape.
So they launched, I wasn't there, I wasn't contributing there at that point, but I was a user, actually.
The launch concentrator, I believe in 2021, maybe, or 22. And then clever, so considerate in a nutshell
is an auto-compounder protocol. So it auto compounds your yields, but instead of compounding
into the underlying, it lets you compound into another yield bearing asset, such as Steve, for
instance, or since Aladdin has been very close with the curve ecosystem in the first days,
you can compound your CRV, for instance, instead of compounding stablecoins. So it's kind of,
it's a protocol that lets you DCA with your DeFi farming, basically. And so that's the first
protocol, it's still around with over 100 million TVL. And the second is a clever that lets you
leverage your CVX farming, basically, with without liquidation. And so the first two protocols are
very deep into the curve and convex ecosystem, while the third one, which is F of X, solves the
problem of decentralized stablecoins, basically. And what I love about the design is that it brings
real decentralized alternative into the stablecoin landscape. And it was the origin of F of X is
actually the USDCT peg in March 23, because Aladdin Dow, with the existing two protocols,
had a treasury, mostly made of USDCT. And they just figured it's such a nonsense
to build DeFi on the most decentralized infrastructure and to rely on centralized stablecoins and to
depend on on trotify events such as the SVB failure. And this is how the idea of F of X
was raised in the first place. And it evolved to what it is today. And today we managed to bootstrap
FX USD to over 100 million market cap as well, while having no VC funding, while doing things
100% organically. Yeah, no, I agree. It feels like a huge failure on the part of the ecosystem.
Sometimes I think the fact that centralized stablecoins have dominance over the stablecoin
market deals like a pretty big failure on the part of proponents of decentralized tech.
And it's really unfortunate that protocols like die and other decentralized
stablecoins haven't picked up more adoption than they have. I mean, there's sizable adoption,
but it's nowhere near where USDCT and Tether are at. There's a lot of regulatory risk there,
and also you have DPG risks and these sorts of off-chain risks. What is the core
value that you think? There's a sort of core tenets that a decentralized stablecoin protocol
should embody. If you had to put characteristics on what an ideal decentralized stablecoin protocol
looks like, what would those be? Yeah, I think for a decentralized stablecoin to work, people need to
trust it to be reliable. So it needs to have a good peg, obviously, and to be liquid enough so
that you can come and buy it and set it in size. And it needs to be collateralized so that the
peg actually stays. So it's not just liquidity, but it's actually a good peg by design and good
backing, and it also needs to be scalable. It all goes back to the stable controllima. It needs to be,
in my opinion, mostly on-chain, because so that you can abstract trust from it and just trust the
code instead of trusting entities and people. And yeah, that's... And it also brings censorship
resistance by being on-chain. So that's all these different key components, I guess, that makes a
good decentralized stablecoin. In my opinion, the beauty of Ethereum and decentralization is that
it abstracts trust. And abstracting trust from finance reduced the risk, right? And it's just like
people just forget about this. And just like the trust fight is used to trust and to have someone
to sue if anything goes wrong, why we can't just avoid trusting people using Ethereum.
And in my opinion, it makes love sense to embrace that technology and to bring... And this is actually
what we do with FOX. We manage to deliver higher risk with lower risk, because there is no trust
involved. And in my opinion, that's a paradigm change that will come at some point with when
the most of the new trust fight guys would be crypto-native and understand that value proposition.
Yeah, I certainly hope so. I mean, there's a centralized stablecoins have a lot of tailwinds.
I think for that to happen, it could happen that decentralized stablecoins take over. But
there would have to be some catastrophic event that really erodes the trust in Tether or USDC
to the point where decentralized stablecoins can come in and start taking that. I don't know
that I think that decentralized stablecoins can slowly start creeping up and building up
issuance to really surpass in a meaningful way the main state of centralized ones.
I don't think they will take over because the centralized one will probably always be more
convenient and scalable. That's a fact. But I also believe that centralized stablecoin will
all eventually disappoint at some point. And at that point, people will need a reliable
alternative to use. And why would you use a more risky stablecoin? So more trusted stablecoin
with low risks while you can most of the time use a decentralized one with higher yields.
The idea is just to offer a reliable alternative. And this is what we're doing and looks like.
People understand it since the protocol has grown pretty well lately.
Yeah, that makes sense. I think also maybe there's still some lingering fear about decentralized
stablecoins, where with USDC, so that might also contribute a little bit. I think also to
generally, they're harder to understand than a centralized stablecoin. Hey, there's an institution
behind this. There's all these banks. There's KPMG audits to save the monies there. I get that
because that's the model that most people are familiar with. With a decentralized stablecoin,
you have to listen to hour one podcast like this to understand what the fuck's going on.
Again, it goes back to that trust paradigm of the old world in a way. But yeah, definitely,
there's a PTSD of USDC. And lots of people I meet, and the first question they ask about
FXUSD is, is it an algorithmic stablecoin? Because they heard about this.
Dangerous. And yeah, now it's fully collateralized with exogenous collateral.
This is a decentralized stablecoin. Cool. Yeah, well, let me get into a little bit of how it works.
And the first time we chatted, you described it as an evolution on the CDP model that maker
introduced the world back in 2016. So maybe using that as a comparison, because I think
a lot of people have that model and understand that model. How does it work and what are the
different components? Yeah, for people used to the CDP model, it's the easiest way to
understand how FX works. It's indeed an evolved CDP design in the way that so FX offers two products.
The first one is a leverage product. So it delivers leverage on ETH and BTC or BTC, you can choose.
Directional leverage without funding costs, without borrowing costs, users just pay a one-time
opening and closing fee. And that's it. And in most cases, they won't have to pay any funding.
It can happen in very rare occasions. But so it brings predictability in the cost.
And the difference with regular CDP is that we abstract the looping. So we give overexposure
to the collateral, just like if you would use a CDP with looping protocols such as DeFi Saver or
Contangor stuff like that to get directional leverage. We abstract it. We include it into the
product. So that's called expositions for the longs, expositions for the short. You get directional
leverage up to 7X, predictable cost, just a one-time fee. And we have this very innovative
liquidation mechanism that prevents any hard liquidation. So you don't get the half or the
entire position wiped out if the market goes on the opposite side. And you get this very
progressive liquidation that keeps you as much exposure as possible and reduce the risk.
So on the leverage side, in a way, it's a zero-stress leverage. It's just a zen
perp, if you want, using the CDP model in the back end. Okay. So maybe we'll stop it there and
go over those different parts yet. So comparing to the CDP model, CDP, you borrow against collateral,
but leverage doesn't include in the protocol. Typically, people get that leverage by going through
some external protocol like DeFi Saver or maybe Instadap. And they're exporting the looping
functionality to that protocol and then bring the collateral back. Yeah, it's a huge pain in
the ass. I've done this. It's just really painful and scary to do. And then you bring the collateral
back and then you're doing this loop and you may get some leverage from that. FFX has this built
in. So you can do up to 7X leverage. And then the other part that you mentioned is that there's a
gradual liquidation mechanism, which means that your collateral isn't liquidated in sort of a
single transaction. It's very progressive. It's progressive, right? So and I guess I've never thought
of this, but what makes that possible and why is it that typically letting protocols don't have a
progressive... It's a very good liquidation mechanism. Yeah, thank you for asking this.
Why the other CDP don't do this is because most of that... We're just lending protocols,
basically. Why wouldn't Aave kind of have this progressive letting mechanism?
Can't do this because they handle each leverage positions individually. So to make the
liquidation profitable, it needs to be large enough so that the keeper, the liquidator,
will actually be profitable by handling the liquidation. And the main difference with
FFX is that all the leverage positions are handled together based on the price ticks,
basically. So we aggregate every position at risk together to process the liquidations,
meaning the liquidations are profitable even if the individual liquidation is very small.
So to illustrate the design, if you're familiar with the LTV concept, each time your leverage
position crosses 88% LTV, the protocol puts it back at 88% LTV, no matter the amount it represents,
the dollar amount, the value of the liquidation, so that your position never reaches 95%
hard liquidation LTV. If that process ever fails and your position reaches 95% LTV,
at that point, the whole position is liquidated. But in most cases, it shouldn't happen because
it works. So you're kind of socializing the liquidation mechanism. Is that exactly where we're
looking at it? Yeah, it's a good way of saying it. It's socialized. Okay, interesting. And no
other DeFi protocol does this, like your landing protocol. Yeah, recently, Fluid came up with a
similar approach. They have this whole base liquidity layer, but it's a way bigger machine,
because it's a whole lending protocol and decks and so on. It's on the FX side, it's way simpler.
It's just two collaterals and a CDP, but they have a similar approach. In a way,
the main difference on their side is, I believe, is that the liquidation penalty can fluctuate,
while on F of X, it's fixed two on five. On Fluid, I believe it goes from one person to eight percent.
Okay, so maybe just to put this another way, say we compare with Aave, like Aave, each position
is can be liquidated and has to be liquidated individually to protect the underlying collateral.
Here, the underlying collateral is kind of pooled to represent all of the positions.
That collateral is going to secure your position as much as it's going to secure
someone else's. And the different positions may have different collateral ratios,
relative to the overall collateral, which is where you get this kind of socialization mechanism.
So someone else's collateral is kind of like backing your position, right?
Not exactly. Your position is actually like your position collateral ratio is
monitored. So there's no, you're not actually, each long position has its own collateral,
but it's all pooled together and all the leverage positions are monitored together.
So and instead of of liquidating each position individually, you look at what's at risk on each
position, considering the current price, and you liquidate everything altogether. Is that, is that
easier in your way? Yeah, I think, I think that makes more sense. Okay. And what kind of
complications this is in this, this, because there's always trade-offs, right? So like, what's the,
so trade-off of this approach? Regarding other lending, lending,
liquidation design, or, or even CTP, I think it's just, it's just better, because it enables
higher LTV. This is how we, we managed to deliver up to seven X wide on RV, for instance,
you would get like five X stops on, on E for BTC. It gives us like, by liquidating way more
progressively, it's, it's, it's, it's kind of, it's more secure in a way.
Right. But is it, are there like unintended trade-offs like, for example, like the, the, you know,
the, the fees you can charge a lower, or like, you know, liquidations, liquid, like, liquidators
are less efficient. Like, there must be some, some trade-off, right? On the liquidation side,
no, I don't think, I don't, I don't think, I can't think of any trade-off here. It's actually a
more efficient way of, of doing things. Now, I don't think of any trade-off on that, on that side.
Actually, the, the cost of liquid, of the liquidations is like the liquidation penalty,
which is a keeper bounty. It's actually the same. It's way lower than on, on other money markets,
for instance. If you compare with Aave, when you get liquidated in Aave, I believe it's,
it's at least five percent penalty, or maybe ten. And, and the, the liquidation of the TV on,
on E, or, or Steve, is something like 80%, why did it, it's 88, on F of X. And, and when you get
liquidated, you can get up to 50 percent of your position instantly with repaid. That's a hit, you
know, on F of X, it can be as small as just 0.1 percent of your position, like that. If the price
just touches it and goes up again, you don't, don't get wiped more, the penalty is 0.5 percent.
Our money market, it's, it's way more secure and efficient, and it brings like a relief in terms of
how you see liquidations. To compare with a, a regular centralized perp, it's still, since it's
on-chain, it's the, the liquidation of the TV, even if it's a partial progressive
liquidation, is still lower than on, on their centralized perp, because liquidations are
processed with a 90, 90.5 percent of the TV on, on Binance, for instance. But it's a, it's just a
different approach, you know, it's, and so with this approach, you have near capital, 100% capital
efficiency, like, border lending is really 100%. Now it's, it's still over collateralized, but it,
it's since, since it's more efficient, we, it's, we can have a lower collateral, overall collateral
ratio than on other CDPs. So it's more capitalization than, than previous CDPs. It's still, obviously,
less scalable than a centralized table coin, obviously, because it's over collateralized, but
still, it brings a better compromise than anything before.
Okay. I'm looking at the website, it says that four billion dollar, well, almost five billion
dollars have been liquidated last month on other perp solutions and FX has zero liquidations.
Yeah, because, like the hot liquidations only happened once, it was in the first days of the,
the current iteration of the protocol, when there wasn't enough keepers processing the, the, the,
the liquidation break. So that's the, some position reaches, reached, reached 95% LTV and got
liquidated. But since that events, it wasn't on February 2nd or something like that, there was a
massive liquidation event on the market. And since that dates, there was no hot liquidations
on FX. Some got proportionally reduced in a way, but there was no hot liquidations.
And the main, the main, the main point of, of this design is that the leverage users keep as much
exposure as possible to recover with the market, if the market ever recovers. If they made a bad
trade, it won't, it won't save them. You know, if the market just crashes and goes to zero, they
would go to zero, you know, but way more progressively than on any other on-chain leverage solution.
And another thing you mentioned is that there's no funding rate for the leverage trades. You just
have this one-time fee. Yeah, that's great. What's unique, what's unique about this approach?
What is it an able? It's been, it has been done before by liquidy, for instance,
with the LUSD. It was similar in a way. People would just pay a one-time opening fee. But the
main difference here is that LUSD couldn't scale because they had massive tag issues.
Like the, the LUSD tag is not reliable enough to actually hold the LUSD because you end up buying
it at 1.05 and setting it at 0.99. So it's not reliable enough. And we fixed this by still having this
just fixed one-time opening fee and closing fee. But we only add a small funding
if the stable current is ever de-pegged. And that funding is just like most of the fees generated
by the protocol are distributed to a stability pool that acts as a peck keeper, to attract more
USDC, earning that, that's organic gains and helping with supporting FX/USD spec.
So we have this organic peck keeping mechanism that, that just work and that
lets FX/USD scale pretty well since we launched earlier this year.
Yeah, let's, let's talk about the, that stability mechanism, the stability pool. And there's,
there's also, I think, like, I guess FX save is also related here.
Yeah, correct. Yeah. So, so, like, what's really impressive here, I think is the yields,
which range between like 10 and 20%. Now, you know, those, those approach
Terra level, anchor level yields, but yeah, why, why, why is this sustainable? How, how is this
sustainable? Yeah, it's, it's a good question. Indeed, FX save, which is the main yield strategy
on the FFX protocol has since we launched it has been one of the best yield, stable yield in DeFi.
If you look at the dashboard created by inverse finance called stable yields.info,
you can compare all the main yield bearing stable strategies around such as FX save,
obviously, Estola, stake USR, SCRV, USD, SUSD and stuff like that and most of them.
And if you look at this on different timeframes, you see that FX save has been
both all the time and like the next one is like four points below FX save. And, and that's,
that's a huge success for us. We're very, very proud of this. And most, and the main thing is
that most of this yield is 100% organic and doesn't imply any human active management.
It's 100% small contracts on chain. There's, yeah, nothing to trust as than the code, you know.
And so to understand what, how it works, maybe I can break down the different,
the, the, the peg keeping of FX, USD. So if you understand that
FX protocol is an evolved CDP, whenever people are longing the collateral, it involves selling
the stable coin, right? Because in the backend, the stable coin is sold for more collateral.
So it brings selling pressure. And this is, this is why, for instance,
LUSD ended up under peg or, or, or the, the people getting leverage on liquidity ended up being
redeemed, because LUSD was massively sold. And we sold it with different peg keeping mechanisms.
The first one is that stability pool. On FFX, the stability pool is a YIT strategy that takes
both FX USD, the decentralized stable coin, and USDC as pays assets. And it acts as a peg keeping
mechanism. Each time FX USD is traded below one on, on the main liquidity pool, which is on curve
against USDC. Each time FX USD is traded below one, the USDC from the year strategy will buy
FX USD in the market to put it closer to peg. And each time it's traded above one, it's sold back
for USDC and goes back to the stability pool. So that strategy keeps FX USD's peg. And to
attract capital, the incentives comes from all the org, the, the fees generated by the protocol.
At the moment, the protocol generates close to $1 million a month. And most of it is distributed
to the stability pool or the governance token lockers. Okay. So just, just to stop there for a second.
So, so the protocol does rely on, on USDC, at least in the stability mechanism to find its price.
Yeah, it's not backed by USDC at any point. But like USDC is the, like, if you wanna, if you wanna
any assets on chain to be pegged to USD, it's, it's pegged to USDC or USDT. And actually on chain,
USDC is the most liquid. So this is why USDC currently is the most liquid,
DeFi stablecoin around. So if you want, is it safe to say that, like, this mechanism, it wouldn't be
possible without an on-chain stablecoin that has a really high peg stability?
The other option would be companies that could handle their redemption with real dollars, for
instance. But yeah, since we don't wanna rely on, I guess the biggest company that does this
currently is, is Circle and, and, and Tether. But the most liquid on-chain is, is Circle with USDC.
Right. Okay.
That's, currently the obvious choice. At some point, if we scale a FX USD enough,
we may not need it anymore. And people will build liquidity with FX USD because they want
to be paired with FX USD. But when you build the stablecoin, if you want it to be liquid and at
peg, you need to build liquidity with currently the, the most obvious choice is USDC.
Right. And, and so if there was a USDC deep peg, you know, highly unlikely, but like it happened
before, right? What happened before? And they actually triggered the creation of F of X.
If the stability pool cannot accept USDC, like the USDC peg is monitored. And when,
if the other deep pegs, the stability pool won't accept more, any more USDC. So it's exposed,
but protected from USDC deep peg. So you get exposure to both assets, FX USD and USDC,
but it's protected from any USDC deep peg. So the main risk here in that strategy,
for any LP is the FX USD peg. And this is why there's different layers of peg keeping. The first one
is the stability pool itself. And, and, and so the, the yield comes from the protocol economic
activities. So people taking leverage, they pay this one time, she told you about, they can have in
some situation a funding and I'll go through this in a, in a second. And, and most of the leverage
positions are backed by yield generating assets such as wrap state if, and that yield also goes to
the stability pool. So if, but if it's not enough, so actually whenever FX USD is traded
below one is actually below 0.998, the stability pool buys FX USD to the market. But if there's not
enough USDC into the stability pool, so whenever the ratio of USDC goes below 5%, we may not have
enough USDC to support the peg. So in that very situation, all the leverage positions get a small
funding cost applied to their position. It's temporary and it's, it's here to support the peg. And that
funding cost is the RV boring cost of USDC. And that goes to the stability pool to attract more USDC
deposits that will support the peg and, and then cut the funding because as soon as the distribution
of USDC goes above 5% again, then the funding is off. But if it's not enough, there's, you know,
different layers, you always have to, you know, anticipate what could go wrong. If it's not enough,
and FX USD starts to debug for too long. It means when the EMA 42 minutes of FX USD on curve
goes below 0.998, so it's pretty small debug, but long enough to be
modicable, we trigger what I call the debug mode. And in, in that situation, people can no longer
open any long positions. So it prevents any further selling pressure on FX USD.
And at that point, a second layer of funding is applied to their leverage positions,
which is way higher. It's 5 or 10 times the USDC boring costs. I don't believe it happened yet,
because the previous layer of the keeping were always been enough. But in that situation,
it brings a very high incentive for leveragers to, for either leveragers to repay to close their
loans, because they can buy FX USD cheaper and close with a bigger profit, and they can avoid
these high fundings. If they keep their loans open, then it brings a very like massive yield
to the stability pool, just attracting USDC that will
cut, repack FX USD quickly and cut the fundings. And there is one last layer of
peg keeping mechanism, which is the redemption. When FX USD is in, in the peg mode, people can,
can buy it and redeem it against the collateral minus a 0.5% redeeming fee. So that sets the
worst-case scenario of peg at 0.995, basically.
One question here, like, you know, I'm looking at the stable yields dashboard, which is great, by the way.
And, you know, the yield, the 30 average is almost six points above the second position,
but only has, well, has less than half the, the TBL. And if you look at Athena, Athena has
5.7 billion in TBL with also about the same 30 average. There's about 100 million in TBL as
we're recording this on September 3rd. You know, with yields, with yields so attractive and a mechanism
that appears to be sustainable and sort of safe. Why, in your view, why isn't there more TBL on FX?
There's probably different reasons for that. First thing is that we are doing things
100% organically. There is no VC backing. So there's, so we don't get it. We had to make all
our connections ourselves, you know, just by reaching out to people and meeting people into
events and stuff like that. And the overall protocol TBL is over 400 million now, and it's been built
100% organically. So it takes, and I guess it takes time to build, as you said it previously,
it takes time to build trust towards a decentralized stablecoin. So for people to actually understand
that the team won't regret pull, that it's actually secure and there's the liquidation mechanism
works and the pecking mechanism works and so on. And that the yield will also be
sustainable. The stablecoin will be liquid enough so that people can come and exit in size and
stuff like that. It takes time to build that. And we've done that and we keep doing it and reaching
out to getting in touch with more and more people. But I guess it takes longer when you're doing
this just organically and without any massively backed token, a TGE event to come and stuff like
that, you know, because the token has been liquid from scratch with fixed emissions over the next
50 years. And yeah, there's, it's probably less speculative in a way than other VC-backed projects.
And then obviously ifina is not exactly a DeFi product, it's highly centralized and realized on
uncentralized fundings, which makes it obviously more scalable. And if we were having five billion
right now, the yield wouldn't be that high. But what we observed over the past few months and
scaling the protocol to over 400 million is that it actually scales by growing progressively.
The more trivial there is into the stability, the more leverage activity we observe on the
leverage side and the more fees we collect. And when you look at the collected fees over each month,
it's pretty clear that there's a pattern of of, of, of stabilizing these fees and having them
weigh more steady over time and growing steady. I don't know if I exactly answered your questions,
I went to all different topics, but I guess doing things, you can do not VCs and 100% on-chain.
It's, it's the primary harder to, to, to, to scale a protocol that way. But in my opinion,
and our mission with F of X and added in that was to build stuff that will last for decades,
if not centuries. And so yeah, we're in here for the long term.
Do you think that like with, you know, the track record now that you've built, you know,
this TVL and, and a, you know, a, a, a pack that has held and kind of demonstrated that this works,
do you think that it would be useful to now go and like raise money to accelerate growth,
to accelerate, you know, fundraising into the protocol, marketing, etc. Is that something you
consider? We don't consider raising money from VCs because it's, but people are free to buy the
token on, on the market. And it's, if people do it actually helps because there's other strategies,
which are incentivized with the, the token. But we're, but it, it definitely helps on one side is
that when we talk to new funds and stuff like that, and it's way easier now that the, the stable
coin is more liquid and, and the protocol is bigger than in the beginning. So it helps to, to raise,
in a way, stable TVL for the stability pool, because the more TV and there is in the stability pool,
the more volume we can process on the leverage side because it keeps, and so yeah, it helps on,
and we, and we've definitely seen the difference. For instance, we were discussing it with Paul,
another team member that went to ETH CC with me this year, as well as last year,
and we've seen a major difference between the two editions in how people were interacting with us.
Like when we were talking to people and other builders last year, it, we felt like they were,
oh, that's interesting. Let's see how it goes, you know, and now it was mostly, wow, guys,
congrats on the, congrats on the growth. And it definitely, it's way easier to, to build
partnerships when people already heard about the protocol and, and start trusting it.
So I wanted to switch gears a little bit. You, you guys published an article a couple of days ago
on your Twitter, it's your theorem security model and strategic importance of decentralized
stable coins. Yeah, give me a gist of like what you're arguing for in this article and,
you know, how, how you're thinking about, you know, theorem security long term.
Yeah, so yeah, the idea of the article, this was, it was to, to point out that the value secured
bar, if you're in, in, in centralized asset mostly, which is, which are real-world assets
and use dt and use dt and stuff like that, is going so high that at some point, these guys and,
and today, instead of tomorrow, it could be another entity has a major weight into any,
into the, the, the, the protocol security. For instance, if there is any,
half fork tomorrow for a new update, for instance, and that, that major centralized entity doesn't
want to support it. What's going to happen, you know, and by supporting all these centralized
entities, we make that possible. We make, it's made, it may not, it may not be a technical issue,
because obviously it's, it's very hard to compromise proof of stake. But it could be a
political issue, at some point, and, and, and economic issue. And, and the idea is not to say,
as I told you earlier, that we should replace centralized stablecoins with decentralized,
but the idea is, is that we want to make sure that there's always an, an alternative that you
can use in most cases, and just use centralized solutions when it's absolutely needed. And I like
to compare some decentralization with privacy, for instance. It's not, it's not white or black,
you know, it's not, it's not binary. You don't, you cannot be totally private and anonymous on
internet. It's, it's a, it's a scope, you know, and I know people decentralize this decentralization,
this scope is some kind of a meme, but it's actually true. You do your best, you just do your best,
and if you can, you can use private product in most cases, like let's say, in for search
engines, you can use DuckDuckGo most of the time, and if you don't find the answer,
then you'll go on Google, and it's actually better than using Google all the time and giving them
all your private data. And it's, I think it's pretty much the same thing. If, if you can
achieve what you want to achieve with your stables using a decentralized one,
there is no point in using a centralized one. So if you can get better yields while staying
decentralized, you should just do it. And whenever you want to off-ramp because today on, on off-ramp
goes through centralized solutions, then you can go with the centralized solution for that very
moment. But in, yeah, that's, I guess that's the main idea of what we wanted, the, the message we
wanted to pass with that article. I mean, I think, I think it makes sense to
kind of promote the use of decentralized stablecoins, but like, yeah, as we were saying earlier in
the conversation, it's like, you know, at this point, USDC and Tether are so ingrained. It's like,
it, it almost feels like a little bit of like Ethereum's Achilles heel that, you know, we've built,
like the ecosystem has built all this amazing decentralized infrastructure only to recreate,
kind of similar systems that exist in tradfi. And yeah, that the, it's not, it's not clear like
what, what the solution is there to kind of mitigate for this as a, as a space.
Yeah, I think it's shame, especially when there are actual, actual reliable alternatives. It's always
a compromise between decentralization and, and convenience, you know, if it's convenient, if it's
not convenient, you won't do it. It's just like ecology as well is, is, is very similar.
People won't recycle if it's a pain to recycle. If they can just do it very easily, they will do it.
And, and, and, and, and now that I believe we, we brought a design that is a convenient, reliable,
secure, and, and, and with act, attractive yields, then why are you using anything else, you know?
Now, one, one other thing I wanted to talk about is kind of where FX sits within the broader
Perps landscape. So, you know, you guys are competing with gearbox and GMX and hyperliquid
and D Y DX. And it's a, it's a market that's very dynamic and that's changing all the time.
It's like two years ago, D Y DX was, you know, sort of leading that market, had a lot of traction.
And now that's sort of lost prominence. Now everyone's kind of focused on hyperliquid.
And I think it is, there is a big part of that that is driven by incentives that's also like
driven by capital and, you know, like hyperliquid has a lot of money. How do you guys succeed in
that space and, you know, maintain relevance long term when we know that like really well
capitalized projects like D Y DX, you know, have lost prominence in, in such a, in such a
short period. And who knows me? Like maybe hyperliquid in two years when I was like totally irrelevant
and something new came along and it was much more interesting. Yeah, maybe even unknown.
Yeah, I think we mostly do our own path in that market in that very competitive market as you stated.
But we have our own blue ocean. I don't know if you heard about that book, but it's like we
have our niche market in a way because we're not exactly a perp. We're not exactly a CDP.
We're kind of in between delivering zero stress leverage. And for many people getting a leverage
position just is a headache, you know, they don't sleep well and they are very nervous and they get
liquidated. We've seen that James when guy getting liquidated all the time. I mean, if that guy
had been longing or trading on f of X, he would still be rich, you know, and, and we, we bring a
solution to these guys basically. I don't know, I don't know who that is, but I feel his pain.
Yeah, it's a guy on on X that shares his trades and people just observe. And there was another one
fund. I don't remember the name. And these guys just keep getting liquidated in a hyper liquid.
And I've seen there's even a meme saying hyper liquidated. That's a good one because the other
thing is that on all these semi centralized solutions, there is more risk and on the hyper liquid side,
there is a massive trust me pro stuff on the on the Oracle side. And we've seen it recently.
People got liquidity for no reasons on I don't recall what what ticker it cannot happen on f of
X. Everything is hundred person on chain. There's no, there's no, there's no, I mean,
to play devil's advocate here, like, like, you know, there is kind of an oracle and that oracle
is the US is like the treasury bonds that are like backing the USDC,
they're backing the USDC peg, right? Because that that's a mechanism that enables the stability pool
to function. So I think like, sure, there's there's no oracle and there's maybe no centralized oracle,
but there is a reliance on some centralized thing that. Yeah, of course, f of X relies on chain link
as an oracle, just like all DeFi. And obviously, we were talking about Taylor being a
Democles sword for DeFi earlier and and Chaining is another one, obviously. But yeah, as
yeah, there is a reliance on on Chaining on on f of X. And and on USDC spec, yes,
and no, not not exactly because as I told you, like, for instance, the stability pool and FXA,
which is built on top of the stability pool is protected from from any USDC.
Okay, maybe not vulnerable, but like it relies on on the price on that price feed, if you will,
like that, that's kind of the price the equivalent of a price feed. Yeah, but we believe that so far
Chaining is the most secure and reliable oracle provider. And if Chaining fails on the E for PTC
oracle, I guess f of X is going to be the list of your problems. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, it'd be great
to have just like a simulation where that happens just to see like, you know, how we just all get
rugged, like a DeFi dystopian story. Yeah, yeah, just just like build the simulation where, you know,
the chain link oracle price for either BTC just goes off haywire and then what happens?
Well, I don't have because I'm not the technical guy in the team. I don't recall the exact oracle
design. But if I recall correctly, there's different safeguards in the oracle design
on f of X. Looking to the future, like Ethereum aspires to secure hundreds of billions, trillions
in in RWAs, like stable coins are becoming a large part of the kind of crypto narrative.
Institutions are hopping on the stable coin sort of train.
There, I think we all kind of anticipate a proliferation of stable coins with many branded stable coins,
like PayPal is just like one of many, I think that will come. What are the opportunities here?
I think for us as an ecosystem and where does f of X fit in there? Yeah, so again, a very good
question. We actually already see your opportunities. And I think I will also answer in a different
way. One of your previous questions regarding how we can compete and why the TVL is lower than
Athena's, for instance. These products, since they are not hot core defying away, they're CD5 stuff,
they are already institution ready. You know, they can talk to institutions and they can build,
they can sign contracts, actual legal contracts, not spark contracts with these guys. And so that
these institutions can deploy capital. And for instance, usual scale like crazy by onboarding
capital that was had no idea about crypto in the first place. That's crazy. They managed to scale
to 2 billion, if I recall correctly, with people from all around the world that had never done any
transaction. And as a DeFi protocol, this is way harder because these institutions don't want to
hear about this. And hopefully, there's solutions now and there's new protocols filling that gap
between OG DeFi in a way, and institutions. And we're currently working on a product with
different partners such as Lagoon Finance, 9 Summit, Nexus-Mootwald, APC custody solutions to build
tailored product for institutions. So that's institutions could harness the FX save yield
in a very safe way. And you're actually the first person I talk about it publicly.
The idea is to call this FX save, because it would be the FX save without the DeFi risks,
all created and institution ready. So that's a way to embrace the arrival of an institutional money.
And the other way is all these new stablecoins you mentioned. I don't really see them as
competitors, because most of them are very attracted with organic yields, and some of them are already
harnessing them. Many of these new yield-based bearing stablecoins are made of other yield-winning
stablecoins on harnessing on-chain or off-chain yields. And they actually use FX save or stability
pool in the back end. So they contribute to our growth in a way. So it's not just centralized
solution versus decentralized solutions. There is a synergy between the two words, and it's actually
good, because in the first places I could see it in the good guys and the bad guys away,
but actually we can build synergies. And these guys can help us build the
alternative to what they're doing. Well, that's a great note to end on.
Said hey, thanks so much for spending the time on Epicenter day. And yeah, looking forward to seeing
FX go up and to the right. Yeah, thank you very much for having me. If you enjoyed that episode,
feel free to join the Aladdin Dow Discord. It's a very open community. We all started by popping up
on the Discord and asking questions and sharing ideas about the design. So it's always a pleasure
to meet new people and discuss things, discuss DeFi between passionate people.
Great. Thanks again. Cheers. Thank you very much. Bye.